Finding Aid for Philip Juliber Elving papers, 1939-1977
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Philip Juliber Elving papers 1939-1977
Elving, Philip Juliber, 1913-
1.3 linear foot
88291 Aa 2
Professor of chemistry at the University of Michigan. Files relating to University of Michigan and professional organization activities; records relating to his career at Pennsylvania State University and Purdue University.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was transferred from the Department of Chemistry of the University of Michigan 587.
The collection is open to research.
Philip J. Eiving was born on March 14, 1913. He received his A.B. in 1934, his A.M. in 1935, and his PhD in 1937, all from Princeton University.
Elving taught analytical and physical chemistry at the University of Michigan from 1952 to 1972. During this time he served on many departmental and university committees. Previously, Elving taught at Pennsylvania State University from 1937 to 1939, 1949 to 1952, and at Purdue University from 1939 to 1943 and from 1947 to 1949. As a visiting professor Elving taught at Harvard University, 1951-1952, and at Hebrew University in 1966, 1973, and 1981.
From 1943 to 1947 Elving was the division head and later assistant director of the research department of Publicker Industries in Philadelphia which specialized in chemical patents.
As an active member of many professional associations, Elving served on editorial and advisory boards. The author and co-author of many articles, Elving received the Fisher Award in analytical chemistry from the American Chemical Society in 1960 and the Anachem Award from the Detroit section of the same society in 1958. Elving's area of research was the study of chemical and physical properties of inorganic and organic compounds which could be used to determine the compound's presence and amounts. This research led to a theory to explain electrochemical behavior of organic compounds with many practical applications, a method to analyze the constituents of plastics, and a method of measuring other biologically and medically important substances. Elving died in 1984.
The papers of Philip J. Elving consist of 1.3 linear feet of mainly professional correspondence, dating from 1939 to 1977. The collection is divided into five series: Associations, Biographical, Journals, Miscellaneous, and the University of Michigan.
Subjects:
Chemistry.; Elving, Philip Juliber, 1913-; Pennsylvania State University.; Purdue University.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Chemistry.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Elving, Philip Juliber, 1913-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Associations
  Associations consists of 0.25 linear feet of materials on various professional organizations and committees that Elving belonged to, or served on. The series dates mostly from 1950 to 1970 and provides insight in to Elving's professional concerns and commitment to analytical chemistry.
  - American Association of University Professors August 1947-May 1950, undated (Box 1)
  - American Chemical Society
    - Analytical Division
      - General Correspondence November 1944-November 1948 (Box 1)
      - Nomenclature Division August 1949-May 1953 (Box 1)
      - Symposium Committee February 1950-July 1957, undated (Box 1)
    - Council January 1954-January 1958 (Box 1)
    - Fisher Award and Merck Fellowship Award Committees May 1949-July 1964 (Box 1)
    - General Correspondence October 1950-October 1970 (Box 1)
    - History of Chemistry Division March 1956-September 1964 (Box 1)
  - American Society for Testing Metals
    - Absorption Spectroscopy Committee February 1951-January 1953 (Box 1)
    - Chemical Analysis of Metals Committee July 1947-April 1953 (Box 1)
    - General Correspondence March 1943-December 1959 (Box 1)
  - Anachem. News July 1949-August 1962 (Box 1)
  - Analytica Chemica Acta October 1965-March 1974 (Box 1)
  - Electrochemical Society September 1952-September 1963, undated (Box 1)
  - Fulbright Committee October 1958-November 1963 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence October 1946-December 1977, undated (Box 1)
  - Gordon Research Conferences December 1950-May 1966 (Box 1)
  - International Society for Electrochemistry March 1952-February 1975 (Box 1)
  - International Union of Pure and Applied Chemistry October 1962-March 1964 (Box 1)
  - Michigan College Chemistry Teachers Association October-December 1956 (Box 1)
  - Midwest Universities Analytical Chemistry Conference December 1955-October 1975 (Box 1)
  - National Research Council
    - Ad hoc Committee on Analytical Chemistry October 1960-July 1966 (Box 1)
    - General Correspondence August 1958-November 1960 (Box 1)
  - Polarographic Society October 1959-January 1962 (Box 1)
  - Society for Analytical Chemistry September 1958-December 1969 (Box 1)
- Biographical
  The Biographical series includes two folders of assorted materials, including newspaper clippings and photographs. This series is valuable in providing a fairly complete and compact documentation of Elving's life.
  - Newspaper clippings and photographs, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Journals
  Journals consists of four folders of correspondence, 1949-1976, related to Elving's activities as a member of editorial or advisory boards.
  - Analytical Chemistry, April 1950-June 1966, undated (Box 1)
  - Chemical Abstracts, June 1949-July 1963 (Box 1)
  - Critical Reviews in Analytical Chemistry, June 1969-January 1975 (Box 1)
  - Journal of the American Chemical Society, 1971-November 1976 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series (9 folders) includes correspondence dating from 1939 to 1977 and relates to his association with other universities and organizations prior to coming to the University of Michigan.
  - DuPont Grant October 1964-December 1965, undated (Box 1)
  - Harvard University February 1951-December 1954 (Box 1)
  - Pennsylvania State University
    - General Correspondence March 1949-June 1969 (Box 1)
    - Sigma Xi November 1950-January 1953 (Box 1)
  - Princeton University
    - December 1949-June 1963 (Box 1)
    - August 1963-December 1976 (Box 1)
  - Publicker Industries April 1947-May 1952, undated (Box 1)
  - Purdue University
    - General Correspondence July 1939-January 1963, undated (Box 1)
    - Purdue Research Associates February 1948-August 1951 (Box 1)
- University of Michigan
  Of most interest to researchers is the University of Michigan series, which is about 0.5 linear feet and dates mostly from 1950 to 1970. The Chemistry Department files document a variety of topics, including the work of several committees on which Elving served. Also of interest are the files relating to his involvement with the University of Michigan College of Literature, Science, and the Arts, and the Horace H. Rackham, School of Graduate Studies.
  - Board of Governors of Religious Affairs: Curricular Matters Committee July 1959-December 1965, undated (Box 1)
  - Chemistry Department
    - Chairmanship November 1960-March 1978 (Box 1)
    - General Correspondence November 1948-December 1965, undated (Box 1)
    - Gomberg Symposium January 1960-August 1966 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Committee July 1958-October 1959 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Student Program February 1953-April 1958 (Box 1)
    - Honors Committee August 1950-February 1963 (Box 1)
    - Laboratory Space October 1952-August 1965, undated (Box 1)
    - Policy Committee December 1965-June 1972 (Box 1)
    - Qualitative Analysis Courses undated (Box 1)
    - Qualifying Committee January-June 1972 (Box 1)
  - College of Literature, Science, and the Arts
    - Accelerated Programs and Curricular Flexing Committee September 1955-March 1956 (Box 1)
    - General Correspondence March 1960-April 1978 (Box 1)
    - Honors Committee June 1959 (Box 1)
    - Junior Year Abroad Committee September 1959-September 1963 (Box 1)
    - Sesquicentennial Arrangements Committee March-April 1965 (Box 1)
    - Tenure and Promotion Committees October 1968-April 1978 (Box 1)
  - Conflict of Interests Committee June 1977-January 1978 (Box 2)
  - General Correspondence June 1957-August 1966 (Box 2)
  - Hillel Foundation October 1968-January 1970 (Box 2)
  - Institute of Science and Technology May 1960-February 1973 (Box 2)
  - Phi Beta Kappa April 1967-March 1971 (Box 2)
  - Phi Lambda Upsilon May 1940-July 1975 (Box 2)
  - Professional Activities Reports
    - 1968-1971 (Box 2)
    - 1972-1978 (Box 2)
  - Rackham School of Graduate Studies
    - Executive Board June 1961-October 1968 (Box 2)
    - Executive Board Committees September 1955-April 1976 (Box 2)
    - Fellowship Stipends Committee May-June 1964 (Box 2)
    - Research Committee October 1958 (Box 2)
  - Religious Studies Committee March 1969-July 1972, undated (Box 2)
  - Research Club March 1953-February 1973, undated (Box 2)
  - Rhodes and Marshall Scholarship Committee September 1963-July 1966 (Box 2)
  - Russel (Henry Russel) Award Committee June 1963 (Box 2)
  - Science Research Club circa October 1952-October 1969 (Box 2)
  - University Club October 1952, undated (Box 2)
  - University Press Editorial Committee September 1969-July 1975 (Box 2)
  - University Publication Problems Committee April 1963-June 1973 (Box 2)
  - University Senate December 1956-December 1957 (Box 2)
  - Water Resources Committee June 1971-August 1975 (Box 2)
  - Water Resources Policy Committee September 1972-August 1973 (Box 2)